Finding Aid for Marcia Federbush papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marcia Federbush papers 1967-2005, 1970-1990
Federbush, Marcia.
4.4 linear feet
2013120 Aa 2
Papers of Marcia Federbush (1934- ), author of the first study of sex discrimination in a public school and of the first Title IX complaint against a university (University of Michigan). Federbush was inducted into The Michigan Women's Hall of Fame for being at the forefront of the efforts for gender equality. The collection includes correspondence, pamphlets, articles, brochures, and laws regarding gender equality. A significant amount of the collection contains the draft for Federbush's unfinished book about discrimination in public education.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Marcia Federbush (Donor No. 10892 ) in August, 2013
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marcia Federbush was born in Newark, New Jersey on May 25, 1934. In 1956 she married Paul Federbush. Federbush received a B.A. in Psychology from New York University and afterwards earned her Masters’ in Education in Elementary Education from Rutgers University. She also studied Organic Chemistry at Harvard University. In 1970 she began her studies in Systematic Botany and Education at the University of Michigan.
Federbush advocated for the same athletic seasons for males and females. She was a prolific writer and conducted the first study of sex discrimination in a public school, entitled "Let them Aspire! A Plea and Proposal for Equality of Opportunity for Males and Females in the Ann Arbor Public Schools." Federbush actively engaged in Title IX debates and wrote many articles concerning its enforcement. She filed the first Title IX complaint against a university (University of Michigan), for "Gross Discrimination against Women in Athletics." Federbush served on various boards, including the Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights (PEER) from 1979-1984 and the advisory committee of The Sports Project Referral and Information Network (SPRINT). The SPRINT project was a part of the Women's Equity Action League (WEAL) that collected and distributed information on women and girls in sports. In 1988 Federbush was inducted into The Michigan Women's Hall of Fame for her efforts towards gender equality in education, athletics, and the workplace.
The collection contains mostly letters, articles, reports, and essays concerning equality among the sexes. Although most of the collection contains work by Federbush, there are many parts to the collection that were not written by her but may have served as inspiration for her own projects. Throughout the collection, if a folder is not specifically labeled "by Federbush" then there are mixtures of items written by different people contained in the folder. The collection is divided into three series: Equality in Education, Equality in Employment, and Equality in Athletics.
Subjects:
Federbush, Marcia.; Sex discrimination in education.; Sex discrimination in employment.; Sex discrimination in sports.; Physical education for women.; Sports for women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports--History.
- Equality in Education
  Equality in Education series (2.5 linear feet) contains publications (some of which are authored by Federbush), correspondence, workshop papers, and laws about equality in education. There are also pamphlets and booklets about how to create a gender neutral curriculum. The series also contains a section about Federbush's efforts towards creating co-educational physical education classes. There are several folders in the collection that describe Federbush's efforts toward the Achievement Gap Initiative, which aimed to combat racial inequalities in the schools. Box 1 of the series contains a folder of Federbush's personal papers, including Federbush's resume. The miscellaneous folder contains a questionnaire about opportunities in men and women's sports, an article (with edits possibly by Federbush), notes, a workshop pamphlet, nominations of women for the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame, and Blanche Pringle's resume.
  The bulk of the series is the first draft of Federbush's unpublished book, "Let Them All Aspire!" According to Federbush's description, in 1975-1977 she was asked to write a book on sex discrimination in public education. The publisher told her that they could not afford to publish a 700 page book, but that a three book series would be more manageable. Federbush divided the book into three:
  Book 1: The Elementary, Academic, and Vocational Aspects
  Book 2: The Physical Aspects: Physical Education, Athletics and Extracurricular Activities, and Sex-Related Aspects
  Book 3: The Adult Aspects: Employment Practices, Adult Education, and In-Service Training
  Federbush's description of her book can be found at the very front of book section. The assorted notes folder contains a short story entitled "Alice in Wonderland (Revised)", notes, and a review of her book. Finally, there is a folder of correspondence related to the book between Federbush and a woman named Mary.
  - Achievement gap initiative 1990s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor public schools papers 1977-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1972-1999 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum 1972-1989, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - First Draft of Book 1975-1977, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Laws and policies 1972-1991, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1)
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - Physical education 1970s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Publications 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Publications (not by Federbush) 1974-1999, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Workshop and committee papers 1999, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Let Them All Aspire" drafts 1975-1977, 17 folders (Box 2)
  - Assorted notes (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - "Let Them All Aspire" drafts 1975-1977, 8 folders (Box 3)
- Equality in Employment
  Equality in Employment series (0.4 linear feet) consists of articles and reports about equality in employment practices, along with a collection of laws and policies that Federbush collected. There is a folder of miscellaneous papers that contains an affirmative action hearing, pre-employment inquiry guide, and correspondence.
  - Articles and reports 1976-1988, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1977-1995 (Box 3)
  - Policies and laws, 1972-1980 (Box 3)
- Equality in Athletics
  - High School
    - MHSAA materials, 1967-1973 (Box 3)
    - Court cases 1970s-1980s, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Reports and memorandums 1975-2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1975-2001 scattered, bulk 1970s-1980s (Box 4)
    - Federbush essays and articles 1978-2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Federbush speeches and correspondence 1966-2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous papers 1973-2005 (Box 4)
    - Questionnaire packets 1983-1984, undated (Box 4)
    - Task force papers, Ann Arbor Public Schools 1980s (Box 4)
    - Task force papers, Livonia Public Schools 1977 (Box 4)
      (comments by Federbush)
  - Collegiate
    - Articles by Federbush, 1974-2003 (Box 4)
    - Court cases, 1970s-1980s, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1973-2002, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Memorandum on gender equity, by Federbush 1995, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Speeches 1972-2005, 1990s, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - SPRINT Project papers 1970s-1980s, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Title IX Compliance 1995 (Box 4)
    - Laws 1976-1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Newspaper articles 1970s-2000s, 5 folders (Box 5)
Related Collections
The Michigan Veteran Feminists Oral Histories Project contains an interview of Federbush. Housed in the Bentley Historical Library, the collection contains interviews of women who were influential in Michigan's feminist movement.
Harvard's Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America have records of the Women's Equity Action League. This collection contains records of the SPRINT project and some folders of correspondence by Federbush. Below is a link to the finding aid:
http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch00301